PROFESSOR: So today we're going
to be adding to this the
idea of informed search.
And informed search, we're going to add
one key idea, which is in addition
to whatever else the search algorithm
is doing, we're going to have a
function that let's look at a state and
see whether or not we're kind of
hot or cold, are we getting
close to the goal?
OK.
And there are good heuristics
and bad heuristics.
We'll talk about how that
all works today.
But this is the key idea in informed
search, something tells you not just
is it a goal or not, but
are you getting close.
PROFESSOR: So the key object
is a search heuristic.
What is a search heuristic?
It is not what you think of when you
think of the word heuristic.
So just like we use rational in a very
specific way, we use heuristic in a
very specific way.
In common language a heuristic
is a rule of thumb.
It's kind of a generic plan that
you should generally follow--
like look both ways before
you cross the street.
A heuristic for us is something
completely different in
terms of its structure.
A heuristic is a function.
It takes a state of the world
and it returns a number.
So it's a function from
states to numbers.
It doesn't tell you what to do.
It doesn't tell you to look both ways
before you cross the street.
It just tells you whether or
not you're close to a goal.
The heuristic, unlike a search algorithm
which just does its thing--
successor functions.
It doesn't know whether it's a pathing
problem or a pancake problem.
The heuristic knows exactly what's
going on in your search problem.
And it knows about things like
positions and pancakes.
So what does a heuristic do?
If can look at the state of the world
and say, you're really, really far.
In that case it will return
a big number.
It can say, oh, you're getting
close to your goal.
In that case it's going to
return a small number.
And you can already imagine how
this will help us do a search.
We could prioritize on the fringe in
areas where the heuristic tells us
we're kind of getting close.
So let's look at an example
of a heuristic.
Here's a Pac-Man board.
If that's my search problem--
get to the dot--
then I want a function that looks
at the state says how far I am.
Well, I don't know how far I am.
How could I find out how far I am?
I could run the search
problem and find out.
Well that would defeat
the whole point.
So I need some kind of general sense
of whether or not I'm close.
Right?
How am I going to do that?
Well I could do something like, look
at the Manhattan distance--
like this.
I could say, well in order to get there,
if I ignore the walls, I need
to least go 10 to the left
and then five down.
Maybe there's some walls in the way
and I'll have to go further.
But more or less if I'm close to the
dot, in general the Manhattan distance
will be smaller.
If I'm far, in general
it will be bigger.
It's not perfect, but it's something.
And that's in general what heuristics
are going to be.
They're not going to be perfect but
they're going to be something.
You could use the Euclidean distance.
This is even less like the game because
can't go on the diagonal.
But it's still the case that, however
you get to that dot-- including the
fact that you can't move diagonally
and the walls are going
to get in your way--
you still aren't any closer than 11.2.
So these are the kinds of things when we
talk about a heuristic-- a function
from states to real numbers.
Here's another heuristic function.
Remember?
We were in Romania trying to get
to the airport at Bucharest.
And there were a bunch of cities
that we could drive between.
And one thing we could use as a
heuristic of how far we would have to
drive along the roads, is what is the
straight line distance from where we
are to our goal, which is Bucharest?
The graph isn't specific to the goal.
The heuristic is.
So in particular you'll notice things
like, Bucharest is zero distance away
from Bucharest.
That's the kind of thing you
want your heuristic to do.
You want to be zero at the goal.
And Arad, which is about as
far as you get, is far.
And as you get closer--
so closer as this place Sibiu--
you can look it up, it's closer.
So the heuristic is generally telling
us whether they're heading in the
right direction.
And this will help us build
a better algorithm.
How about Pancakes?
Well now you're maybe going to start
to see that heuristic functions are
not as simple as Euclidean
distance on a map.
And then sometimes the map is Pac-Man,
and sometimes the map is Romania, and
sometimes there are some things that
are neither Pac-Man nor Romania.
Heuristic functions on pancakes
is a little harder.
How could I know, say, from a given
pancake stack, how far I am?
That's a little hard.
I know if it's right
then I'm zero away.
But how about here?
How many weighted flip
costs away am I?
I don't know.
So you would have to
think really hard.
And one thing you might come up with is
the number of the largest package
that's still out of place.
The idea being if, the fourth largest
pancake is out of place--
wherever it is--
the only way to get it in place is to
somehow get it to the top, and then
from the top flip the whole stack--
or four and above, if there's
more than four.
So you can convince yourself that,
in fact, this is a heuristic.
And the further I am from a solution in
general, the bigger this number is.
We're going to talk later today more
about how you come up with these
heuristics.
But the point is, it's not always
Euclidean distance.
It is, however, always a function
from states to real numbers.
And smaller means closer to
the goal, in general.